Okay today's דף *daf* is דף כ"ו *daf Chaf Vav*, we pick
up on כ"ה עמוד ב' *Chaf He Amud Bet*, מעוברת חבירו *muberet
chaveiro*. We're dealing with cases in the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* of women
who cannot give birth, either because of an elderly woman or a
woman who is infertile, an עקרה *akarah*,
and the חכמים *Chachamim* said that this woman cannot be made to
drink because it's one of the categories of women that the husband
is obligated to divorce. Why divorce? Because he has to do the
מצוה *mitzvah* of פרו ורבו pru u’revu *pru u'revu*, to which רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* cogently responds, he doesn't have to divorce
her, he could just marry another woman so there's actually no problem
being married to this woman and therefore for our purposes it means
he can make her drink the סוטה Sotah *sotah* water. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* picks up, two lines from the top, אמר רב
נחמן Rav Nachman אמר רבה בר בר חנה *amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Bar Chana*, מחלוקת בעקרה וזקנה *machloket be'akarah u'zkeinah*. This debate
is about an elderly woman or an infertile woman, אבל אילונית ailonit,
דברי הכל לא שותה ולא נוטלת כתובתה lo shotah v’lo notalt ketuvatah.
*aval ayloit divrei hakol lo shotah ve'lo notelat ketubatah*. An אילונית ailonit.
*ayloit*, which is a woman who has more male characteristics, she doesn't
have pubic hair, she doesn't develop breasts, it's a woman that could
not get pregnant, everybody would agree physically it's impossible to get pregnant,
everybody would agree that she would not drink and she would not
take her כתובה ketuvah *ketubah*, he cannot make her drink. Why? This
is not about the מצוה *mitzvah* of פרו ורבו *pru u'revu*, this
is a separate category שנאמר ונקתה ונזרעה זרע shenemar v’niketah v’nizreah zara
*shene'emar veniktah venizra zara*. It says by the סוטה Sotah *sotah* that
she'll be cleansed and give forth seed and have a child, מי
שדרכה להזריע *mi shedarkah lehazria*, which tells you that the whole סוטה
sota, *sotah* category relates to a woman who can have a child,
יצא זו שאין דרכה להזריע *yatza zo she'ein darkah lehazria*, to exclude
this case where it is not possible for her to have a
child. Now the question is why is this different than a woman
who is infertile? But רש"י Rashi *Rashi* indicates that the reason is
is that this is something that was from the very birth there
was this
problem in this person. It wasn't, so presumably that that would not
be limited to an אילונית ailonit *ayloit*, if somebody was born for
example baby without a uterus, you know, that would also be somebody
that would not be in the category of נזרעה זרע zera *nizra
zara*, as opposed to somebody that has, you know, we would have
expected that person to be able to be pregnant but there is
some reason that she is not becoming pregnant, or maybe even just
it was later in her life. But for this person who was
born this way, out of the category. Now this emphasis on the
idea of being able to give birth, and we'll see in a
few in a few minutes the issue about the man and the
man and the question of him being able to to ejaculate semen,
the emphasis on זרע zera, *zara*, I think has a lot to
do with you know the whole focus here, the water goes into
her, she blows up or she doesn't or she becomes pregnant, and
probably a lot of jealousy has to do not just with the
issue about sex itself, but with the concern about you know about
whose child a baby might be, and so it's important to really
note that focus on זרע zera, *zara*, you know in general by
סוטה Sotah. *sotah*. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like
this, מיתיבי *meitivei*, challenge this, המקנא לארוסתו לשומר יבם שלו, אם עד
שלא כנסה נסתרה לא lo. שותה ולא נוטלת כתובתה *hamekani le'arusato lishmor
yevamam shelo, im ad shelo kinsa nistarah lo shotah ve'lo notelat ketubatah*.
A man who does קינוי kinui *kinui* to his ארוסה arusah *arusah*,
woman who's betrothed, not yet married, or שומרת יבם shomeret yavam *shomeret
yavam*, if it her she goes into private with this man before
they actually the husband and wife came together, there was נישואין *nisuin*
or יבום yibum *yibum*, then she cannot be made to drink her
כתובה ketuvah. *ketubah*. That's the principle we learned about תחת אישה *tachat
ishah*, that she has it only applies when they are actually living
married life together. Okay, however if it's after they got married she
did the סתירה *stirah*, then the earlier קינוי kinuay *kinui* would work,
as we also learned. מעוברת חבירו מינקת חבירו לא שותה ולא נוטלת
כתובתה *muberet chaveiro meneket chaveiro lo shotah ve'lo notelat ketubatah*. Similarly or
not similarly but another case of not making a woman being able
to to drink is a a man married a woman who was
a previously married to another man and is still carrying his baby
or nursing his baby. דברי רבי מאיר *divrei Rabbi Meir*, that's what
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says, שהיה רבי מאיר אומר לא ישא אדם
מעוברת חבירו מינקת חבירו *shehayah Rabbi Meir omer lo yisa adam muberet
chaveiro meneket chaveiro*. They do not let somebody marry a woman who
is carrying another man's baby or nursing another man's baby, concern about
the health and the well-being of the baby and if the husband
would be too insistent in terms of having sex or whatever, even
if it would be injurious to the health of the baby, and
he wouldn't be as concerned cause it wasn't his baby, so they
did not let you do that. ואם נשא יוציא *ve'im nasa yotzi*,
and רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, because רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* was very
strict about rabbinic edicts, he says that if they actually did get
married,
he's required to divorce her, ולא יחזיר עולמית *ve'lo yachazir olamit*, and
can never remarry her. So for רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* he was
so strict that if this was the case that it was a
this woman who is a nursing or carrying another man's baby, they
would be obligated to get divorced. And once that's true, then you
can't make her drink the סוטה Sotah *sotah* water. וחכמים אומרים יוציא
וכשיגיע זמנה לכנוס יכנוס *vachachamim omrim yotzi u'ksheyagia zemana liknos yichnos*. No,
he can divorce her and then remarry her or maybe live separately
and then be together with her, and therefore since this is not
a woman that he must get divorced from, you know he can
get back together her once she's after the period of pregnancy and
nursing, then she can be made to drink the סוטה Sotah. *sotah*
water, they are considered a couple. הרובע *Ha-rovah*, so this is a
whole list a ברייתא Beraita *baraita* a whole list of cases that
are debated or are ones which which the woman cannot be made
to drink the סוטה *sotah* water. A young man שנשא עקרה וזקנה
*shenasa akarah u'zkeinah* who marry meaning and he doesn't have children yet,
who married a an infertile woman or an elderly. an elderly woman
ואין לו אשה ובנים מעיקרא and he doesn't himself have,
he hasn't had children from another wife before, לא שותה ולא נוטלת
כתובתה. So again, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma here like our משנה
mishna. says then they have to get divorced and therefore the כתובה
he can't be made to drink the סוטה water. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says יכול לישא אחרת וליפרות הימנה. yachol lisa acheret v’lifrot heimena.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer’s says no, he has to have kids, but
it doesn't mean he has to divorce this woman, he can marry
another woman and therefore they can stay together and therefore he can
make her drink the סוטה water.
אבל המקנא לארוסתו ולשומרת יבם שלו משנכנסה נסתרה aval hamikaneh l’arusato u’leshameret
yavam shelo mishenichnesah nistarah but if somebody did the קינוי kinuy to
the ארוסה or שומרת יבם while they were in that earlier stage
but she went into private only after they became married you know
they they did יבום or the betrothed became married, או שותה או
לא נוטלת כתובה o shotah o lo notalt ketuvah then in that
case the woman can be made to drink or just choose not
to get her כתובה. מעוברת ומניקה עצמו meuberet u’meneket atzmo now if
a man is with his wife when she is pregnant or nursing,
או שותה או לא נוטלת כתובה o shotah o lo notalt ketuvah
obviously he doesn't have to divorce her at that stage and we
assume that you know he'll be careful with the health of the
baby and therefore you know it's just in contrast to the previous
this is obviously quite obvious, in that case she can be made
to drink. הרובא שנשא עקרה וזקנה ויש לו בנים harovah shenasa akarah
u’zekeinah v’yesh lo banim again these are all sort of like the
parallels or the you know the mirror images of the previous case.
If a young man married an older woman or an infertile woman
and he does have children from another wife, או שותה או נוטלת
כתובה o shotah o notalt ketuvah in that case he doesn't have
to divorce this current woman and therefore she can be made to
drink. אשת ממזר לממזר וממזרת לממזר eshet mamzer l’mamzer u’mamzeret l’mamzer if
a ממזר mamzer is married to a ממזרת mamzeret or another woman
a ממזר mamzer can be married to like a גיורת giyoret ואשת
נתין לנתין v’eshet natin l’natin or the same with a נתין natin
ואשת גר ועבד משוחרר v’eshet ger v’eved meshuchrar or the wife of
a גר ger a convert or a freed slave who basically is
like a יהודי Yehudi like a convert, ואילונית v’ailonit or an אילונית,
ailonit או שותה או לא נוטלת כתובה o shotah o lo notalt
ketuvah all those women can be made to drink. Now all of
that would seem obvious all these are good binding marriages so the
גמרא gemara will analyze it in a minute but for now we're
going to focus on the case of the אילונית. ailonit Okay, קתני
מיהא אילונית katani miha ailonit so it says אילונית ailonit and an
אילונית ailonit can be forced to drink. תיובתא דרב נחמן tiuvta d’Rav
Nachman this is a complete contradiction to רב נחמן Rav Nachman you
see that an אילונית ailonit? is not excluded from the category and
if you deal with the פרו ורבו issue you know or you
take רבי אליעזר position she can be made to drink. אמר לך
רב נחמן תנאי היא amar lach Rav Nachman tanna-ei hi it's a
debate of תנאים Tannaim ואנא דאמרי כי האי תנא v’ana d’amri ki
hai tanna I follow the following תנא Tanna דתניא תני ברייתא d’tanya
tani Beraita רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר אילונית לא שותה ולא נוטלת
כתובה Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer ailonit lo shotah v’lo notalt ketuvah
an אילונית aylonit cannot be made to drink שנאמר she'ne'emar ונקתה ונזרעה
זרע zera, מי שדרכה להזריע יצאה זו שאין דרכה להזריע mi shedarkah
l’hazria yatzah zo she-ein darkah l’hazria exactly like I said before that
רב נחמן Rav Nachman, said only somebody who can have seed not
somebody who's completely excluded from that category of having seed. So again
an elderly woman or an infertile is not considered completely out of
the category, who knows the infertile woman might drink the water and
become fertile I don't know if we're saying that that will happen
with the elderly but anyway but as opposed to the אילונית who's
completely excluded from that category.
Okay, ורבנן האי ונקתה ונזרעה זרע מאי עביד ליה v’Rabbanan hai v’niketah
v’nizreah zara mai avid lei so for the רבנן Rabbanan what do
they do with this verse if it's not meant to exclude an
אילונית? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא mibei lei l’chidetanya to tell you what the
ברייתא baraisa. teaches. ונקתה ונזרעה זרע שאם הייתה עקרה ונפקדה דברי רבי
עקיבא v’niketah v’nizreah zara she’im haytah akarah v’nifkedah divrei Rabbi Akiva like
the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk you know that she'll be
blessed with a child but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva makes it even
more explicit even if she was infertile you know and she this
will actually make her be able to have a child.
אמר לו רבי ישמעאל amar lo Rabbi Yishmael so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael felt that that went a little bit too far. אם כן
יסתרו כל העקרות ויפקדו im ken yistaru kol ha’akarot v’yifkedu so you
know if that's true then you're now creating an incentive for people
to do this whole קינוי וסתירה kinui v’stirah a woman who's infertile
will just do this thing and have her husband warn her and
go in private so they'll be able to drink and they'll be
able to become fertile and presumably he did not want to imagine
that this thing could be an incentive for that type of behavior.
וזו הואיל ולא נסתרה הפסידה v’zo hoil v’lo nistarah hifsidah and if
a woman and you're going to tell a woman who's infertile because
she did not go into private with another man who wasn't her
husband she's going to lose out and not be able to have
a baby? Like the whole thing creates enormous injustice. אלא אם
כן מה תלמוד לומר ונקתה ונזרעה זרע ela im ken mah talmud
lomar v’niketah v’nizreah zara so what is the פסוק pasuk saying when
it says she'll be able to bring forth a seed? שאם הייתה
יולדת בצער תלד בריוח she’im haytah yoledet b’tzaar teled b’revach it means
yes it'll be easier it'll be better but it's not going to
go from being infertile to being fertile that if it was painful
now it
won't be so painful it'll be easy to give birth. נקבות תלד
זכרים nekeivot teled zecharim if she had girls now she'll have boys
because of course boys were preferred in a patriarchal society. קצרים תלד
ארוכים ketzarim teled aruchim if she had short children now they'll be
tall because it's very funny to show how you know these things
the societal norms
and preferences, the fact that the tall people tend to have
more benefits in society than short people, advantages. שחורים תלד לבנים shechorim
teled levanim or
if they were dark-skinned they'll be light-skinned so again quite quite fascinating
as a sort of sociological window. Anyway presumably you know רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael was not concerned that people that women would actually do
this whole trick in order to drink just to make. it better
like this. If it was a radical difference of infertile and fertile,
yes, but something like this, you know, that he wasn't concerned about.
Also interesting to think about the whole issue of, you know, about
like, of IVF and trying to select genes for what type of
child you're going to have, you know, and are there halakhic issues
with that when it's not about dealing with real genetic concerns? Anyway,
here you certainly see that that's how this water would work. אשת
ממזר לממזר. Eshet mamzer l'mamzer. Now, if it's a woman who could
be married to a ממזר, mamzer, like a ממזרת mamzeret or a
גיורת giyoret to a ממזר, mamzer, so that's normal. פשיטא, Peshita, obviously,
that's normal, they're allowed to be married. מהו דתימא Ma d'teima אפושי
פסולים לא לפשיש, afushei psulim lo lifshash, I might think, no, I
would rather a ממזר mamzer and a ממזרת mamzeret don't get married
because their kids are going to be ממזרים. mamzerim. And therefore if
they are married, we shouldn't do this process because that'll keep them
married. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that we are not concerned with that,
you know, people should have a right to be married. אשת גר
ועבד משוחרר, Eshet ger v'eved meshuchrar, how the wife of a גר
ger and a freed slave. So obviously that's a good marriage. פשיטא,
Peshita, obviously. מהו דתימא Ma d'teima דבר אל בני ישראל ולא גרים,
dabber el bnei Yisrael v'lo gerim, I might think it says speak
to the children of Israel and not to גרים. gerim. קא משמע
לן, Kamashmalan, so it's telling you that no גרים gerim are included
in this whole פרשה. parsha. And עבד משוחרר eved meshuchrar is like
a גר. ger. ואימא הכי נמי, V'eima hachi nami, maybe I should
read it in that limiting way. ואמרת ריבוי הוא. V'amarta ribbuy hu.
Okay, ואמרת אליהם V'amarta aleihem say to them, that's expanding it so
don't read it to be excluding גרים. gerim. Now, this could be
a little bit disturbing because it says that a גר ger is
not included in the meaning of בני ישראל, bnei Yisrael, you need
a ריבוי. ribbuy. It could be that it's not saying that he's
not included, I very much hope that it's saying it's not saying
he's not included in the word ישראל, Yisrael, but בני ישראל, bnei
Yisrael, children of Israel, which means that the father was Jewish. Even
so, it is disturbing in terms of the sense that you need
a ריבוי ribbuy and that is not always the case. אשת כהן
שותה, Eshet kohen shota, now the wife of a כהן, kohen, back
to the משנה. פשיטא, Peshita, obviously, why should it be different? מהו
דתימא Ma d'teima והיא לא נתפשה אסורה. v'hi lo nitpasa asura. The
פסוק pasuk says, 'and if she and this woman wasn't raped,' and
therefore the husband is afraid that she is willingly sleeping with this
other man. And from there we learn that if a woman is
raped, she is not forbidden to her husband. הנתפשה מותרת, Ha-nitpasa muteret,
so that if she is raped she is permitted to her husband.
וזו אף נתפשה אסורה, V'zo af nitpasa asura, but since by the
case of the wife of a כהן, kohen, even if she is
raped she becomes forbidden to her husband, that's a whole separate discussion,
but since that's true and since the פסוקים pesukim make it implicit
that if she's raped she won't be forbidden to her husband, I
might think the פסוקים pesukim are not talking about the wife of
a כהן. kohen. אימא לא תשתה, Eima lo tishte, maybe she shouldn't
be in this category. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that she is, doesn't
need a פסוק pasuk to tell you otherwise, just חז"ל chazal saw
no reason to exclude. ומותרת לבעלה. U'muteret l'ba'ala. Now, once she drinks,
she can go back to her husband. Now obviously that's obvious, why
should the wife of a כהן kohen be any different? פשיטא, Peshita,
obvious. אמר רב פפא במסתבנה. Amar Rav Papa b'misnavna. So in a
woman that is her health is, you know, is getting worse. She's
and she's showing signs of illness. And we knew, we heard before
that a woman who is guilty, but that she had זכות, zechut,
she wouldn't blow up right away but she would gradually, gradually, you
know, start falling apart and you know her health
would, she'd get ill and her health would go down, her well-being
would go down. So the גמרא gemara says, so therefore I might
think that she shouldn't be with her husband because maybe that's a
sign that she is guilty. So the גמרא gemara says, מסתבנה הא
בת קמיה? misnavna habat kamaya? No, so the גמרא gemara actually says,
you know what, if she's showing those signs that we identify with
a woman
who is guilty but who is having the sort of punishment delayed,
then you're right, the husband shouldn't sleep, that proves that she is
guilty. Which first time we're hearing that. So anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, במסתבנה דרך איברים, b'misnavna derech evarim, no. It means that
it's not like her belly and her thighs as the תורה Torah
speaks about it, but it's like she's got a headache and you
know other parts of her body are bothering her, so she's not
feeling well, but it's not the symptoms that we would identify with
this delayed consequence of the drinking. So the גמרא Gemara says okay,
מהו דתימא, ma d'teima, so then what's the חידוש? chidush? If it's
not the symptoms, I might have thought הזינא זנאי, Hazinnai zannai, maybe
she did commit adultery. והא דלא בדקו המים, V'ha d'lo badku amaya,
so why aren't we seeing the normal symptoms of like things happening
to her even in a small way beginning to happen to her
thigh and her stomach? והא דלא מסתבנה כארחא, Ki v'hai d'lo misnavna
k'orchai, the reason it's not having the normal effect, משום דבאונס אנסה,
mishum d'be-ones anai, because she did it and she was compelled.
And remember this is the wife of a כהן. kohen. So on
the one hand she didn't have any fault, she was not to
blame. On the other hand she's still forbidden to her husband because
even though she was raped it was sex with another man and
that makes the wife of a כהן kohen forbidden to her husband.
So maybe these symptoms I'll interpret them as to indicate she's not
guilty, but the כהן kohen should know that she actually was raped
and therefore forbidden to him. And that's why it's a different type
of a symptom. Maybe that's how we should interpret it. Okay. והא
דלא בדקו המים כהא משום דזנאי ולגבי כהן אסירה, V'ha d'lo badku
k'ha mishum d'zannai v'legabei kohen asira, she should be forbidden to the
כהן, kohen, קא משמע לן kamashmalan that we are not concerned with
that, we're not going to make that up out of thin air.
I do have to say that it is of course disturbing that
it uses the word זנאי, zannai, you know,
fornicated, you know, committed adultery, in a case where she was raped.
It's bad enough you know that she's forbidden to her husband. husband
כהן kohen when she's raped and actually be using this term. I
mean, again, the גמרא Gemara is sort of using it as a
shorthand term, but it's still
quite disturbing. Could've said דאבעלה de'ivla that she that she actually was
that she had intercourse. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אשת
סריס סוטה, Eshet seris sota, the wife of a סריס saris can
be made to drink, a man who cannot have children. פשיטא Peshita
obviously. מהו דתימא מבלעדי אישך רחמנא והאי לאו בר הכי הוא. Mah
de'teima mibila'adei ishecha rachmana v'hai lav bar hachi hu. It says that
somebody slept with you other than your husband, and he is not
in this category. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that we don't say that.
Now, what does this mean he's not in this category? Okay. So
רש"י Rashi says he is able to have intercourse and have an
erection; he's just not able to have children. And so, and
there's also an interesting question about whether he's whether he's a פצוע
דכא, ptzuah dakah, whether or not they're able to stay married. רש"י
Rashi makes it a special case. So this is not a פצוע
דכא; ptzuah dakah; he's just somebody, you know, פצוע דכא ptzuah dakah
is a very particular injury, and this person is just not able
to have kids. So what's fascinating though is the גמרא Gemara. suggests
he's not a בר הכי bar hachi even though it doesn't say
זרע zera. by the man. It says somebody slept with, but it
does say ושכב איש אותה שכבת זרע ונעלם מעיני אישה, v'shachav ish
otah shichvat zera v'ne'elam mei'einei ishah, right? A man slept with her
שכבת זרע. shichvat zera.
And therefore the זרע, zera as I said before, is a very
big focus. So therefore maybe if he can't have זרע, zera. it's
the same way, you know, it's out of the category. This tells
you no, it's in the category. Just like we concluded, you know,
other than the position of רב נחמן, that an אילונית was in
the category even though she can't have זרע, zera. he's also in
that category as well. על ידי כל העריות מקנא. Al yedei kol
ha'arayot m'kani. Now, it also applies even if he's saying I don't
want you to be in private with your brother, I'm afraid that
you two might be having an affair. פשיטא Peshita obviously, you know,
that's just another form of adultery and it'd be even worse. No.
מהו דתימא נטמאה נטמאה שתי פעמים Mah de'teima nitme'ah nitme'ah shtei pe'amim
because it says that she became טמאה tamei when she was with
this man, אחד לבעל ואחד לבועל, Echad l'baal v'echad l'boel, which tells
you that when if she's with this man or before it's been
proven and she's a סוטה, she's forbidden to her husband and to
the potential
paramour. היכא דקמיתסר בזנות. heicha d'kamitssar b'haznut. So if she is, that
would be, so therefore if this act of adultery makes her forbidden,
then to the בועל, boel, right? That's the case we're talking about,
when an act of adultery would make her forbidden both to the
husband and to this man. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, but in this
case where it's her brother, הוי אסורה וקיימא, hovei assura v'kayma, since
she's already forbidden to him. So the idea that this act will
make her forbidden to her husband and the man isn't true cause
she's already forbidden to the man. אימא לא, Eima lo, maybe that'll
be categorically excluded. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that it is not excluded.
Okay. חוץ מן הקטן וממי שאינו איש. Chutz min hakatan u'mi she'eino
ish. Also if she says don't be with this minor, even though
an act of adultery with a minor once he's nine years old
would be considered a boy, once an act of adultery. Nevertheless, because
he's not a man, it does not, it's not included in this
category. איש אמר רחמנא ולא קטן. Ish amar rachmana v'lo katan. ושכב
איש אותה שכבת זרע. v'shachav ish otah shichvat zera. Man slept with
her. ושאינו איש, v'she'eino ish, and also somebody who's not a man.
לאתויי מאי? L'matyei mai? Who is this excluding? אילימא לאתויי שחוף. Ilima
l'matyei shachuf. Maybe it's a שחוף. shachuf. רש"י says it's somebody who's
like, you know, their body is falling apart. It's clear from the
context anyway it means that he cannot have normal, he can have
some intercourse but not normal and he can't have, you know, ejaculation
similar to the סריס saris before. והאמר שמואל שחוף מקנא על ידו
ופוסלו בתרומה. Ha'amar Shmuel shachuf m'kanin al yado u'poslo b'terumah. שמואל Shmuel
says that a שחוף shachuf you do do קינוי kinuy, just like
we said by the סריס, saris, and also if he had intercourse
with a with a with a כהן, kohen, the daughter of a
כהן, kohen, she now becomes invalid, not a wife, a daughter of
a כהן, kohen, she now becomes invalid to eat תרומה terumah because
she's had,
if she was somebody that was פסול, pasul, if he was say
maybe like let's say he was a חלל chalal or something of
that nature. Okay. He could invalidate this woman from being able to
have her כהונה kehunah status, her בת כהן bat Cohen status. So
the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, Peshita, oh that's all obvious. No. מקנא
על ידו פשיטא, M'kanin al yado Peshita, obviously, I mean, מהו דתימא
אם נחפת ושכב איש אותה שכבת זרע אמר רחמנא והאי לאו בר
הכי הוא, Mah de'teima im niphat v'shachav ish otah shichvat zera amar
rachmana v'hai lav bar hachi hu, similar to what we said by
סריס, saris, not exactly clear why we would've treated this any different.
Maybe if he can't have זרע. zera.
Oh, I'm sorry. This is now before we were talking about the
husband, this is the flip, this is about the man. Right, cause
you could have imagined that the husband doesn't have to be able
to have seed, but the jealousy is about the sleeping with the
other man who can impregnate her. So maybe in this case when
the man he is suspected of cannot is in cannot ejaculate, maybe
that would be excluded. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that the זרע aspect
is not necessary. ופוסלו בתרומה U'poslo b'terumah now if this man sleeps
with a בת כהן bat Cohen and he's פסול, pasul, he can
make her פסולה pasula as well in a totally different case. פשיטא
Peshita obviously. No. מהו דתימא לא יחלל זרעו אמר רחמנא Mah de'teima
lo yecheilel zaro amar rachmana that when a man sleeps with a
בת כהן bat Cohen he, you know, let's say a חלל, chalal,
he makes her חללה chalala and the kid'll be, you know, and
the kid'll be also a חלל chalal and have that status.
So since we learn now that she and the child become פסול
pasul through the through this act of intercourse, you know, if she
becomes pregnant. דאית ליה זרע לחלל, de'is lei zera l'chalal, if he
if this can produce a child then she becomes a חללה, chalalah,
דלית ליה זרע לא לחלל, de'lais lei zera lo l'chalal, but if
she can't produce a child because the man is not able to
have semen, is not fertile, or you know, is not able to
impregnate her, קמשמע לן kamashma lan that that doesn't matter. Okay. ואלא
למעוטי עובד כוכבים. ve'ela l'mutei oved kochavim. So now we're back. What
does או איש, o ish, what does you can't do קינוי kinuy,
about a man that's not a man? Somebody who's not a man.
Who is it referring to? Maybe it means a non-Jew. והאמר רב
המנונא עובד כוכבים מקנא על ידו. ve'ha'amar Rav Hamnuna oved kochavim mekaneh
al yado. No,
you can do קינוי, don't be with this non-Jew. ופוסל בתרומה, u'posel
b'terumah, and he can make this woman who's a בת כהן bas
kohen invalid to eat תרומה. terumah. מקנא על ידו פשיטא, mekaneh al
yado peshita, obviously says the גמרא. Gemara מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I
might have thought מ"אשה" ו"אשה" me'isha v'isha שתי פעמים, shtei pe'amim, אחד
לבעל ואחד לבועל, echad l'ba'al v'echad l'bo'el, since we learn from the
פסוק pasuk that when she does it, if she did this act
she's forbidden to the husband and to the man, so similarly to
like we would have thought before, היכא דחזיא להזנות, heicha d'chazya l'haznus,
that's only this whole פרשה parsha only applies if this act is
the thing that would make her forbidden to this man. אבל הכא,
aval hacha, by the case of a non-Jew, הא אסורה וקיימא, ha
asura v'kayma, since she's already forbidden to the non-Jew, אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe this whole פרשה parsha doesn't apply, קמשמע לן kamashma lan
that it does. Okay. ופוסל בתרומה פשיטא, u'posel b'terumah peshita, and invalidate
her for תרומה, terumah, obviously. מהו דתימא mahu d'teima ובת כהן כי
תהיה לאיש זר u'bas kohen ki siheye l'ish zar רחמנא rachmana דבר
הויה de'bar havayah אין in דלאו בר הויה de'lav bar havayah לא.
When what does the פסוק pasuk we learn out that when she's
you know with a man that she's forbidden to it makes her
invalid is it's you know if she is when she is with
a foreign man, okay, so maybe only when that intercourse happens with
a man which in theory she can be of הויה, havayah, she
could be married to. But maybe somebody who in theory who couldn't
even be married to, even in theory, maybe it's considered so irrelevant
that it would not make her make her forbidden? קמשמע לן דפסיל
kamashma lan d'pasil מדרבי יוחנן. mi'derabi Yochanan.
From רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan we learn that nevertheless she does become
invalidated. דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי ישמעאל d'amar rabi Yochanan mishum rabi
Yishmael מנין לעובד כוכבים ועבד שבא על הכהנת ועל הלויה ועל בת
ישראל שפסלוה? mamin l'oved kochavim v'eved she'ba al hakohenes v'al haleviyah v'al
bas yisrael she'pasluha? How do we know that if a non-Jew had
intercourse with a כהנת kohenes or a לויה leviyah or even a
בת ישראל bas yisrael that makes her sort of invalid in the
sense of you know being like a חלל, chalal, חללה? chalalah? שנאמר
she'ne'emar ובת כהן כי תהיה אלמנה וגרושה, u'bas kohen ki siheye almana
u'grusha, actually whatever בת ישראל. bas yisrael.
Anyway
the specific aspect of the פסוק pasuk something talk about more, but
anyway, שנאמר she'ne'emar ובת כהן כי תהיה אלמנה וגרושה. u'bas kohen ki
siheye almana u'grusha. מי שיש לו בה אלמנות וגירושין, mi she'yesh lo
bah almanus v'gerushin, יצא עובד כוכבים ועבד שאין לו בה אלמנות וגירושין.
yatza oved kochavim v'eved she'ein lo bah almanus v'gerushin.
Because we learn from a פסוק pasuk that it speaks about a
case of divorce or widowed by a בת כהן, bas kohen, so
that you know the type of intercourse that could would not be
a problem you know under the right circumstances would be somebody that
you could be married to and be a widow or a divorcee
of, but somebody who you can't be that will always create invalidity.
Okay. At least make a בת כהן bas kohen a חללה chalalah
and as I said by בת ישראל bas yisrael it's a different
category. Anyway. Okay. So now ואלא למעוטי מאי? ve'ela l'mutei mai? So
what are we excluding? אמר רב פפא למעוטי בהמה, amar Rav Papa
l'mutei behemah, דאין זנות בבהמה. de'ein znus b'vehemah. It's excluding a בהמה.
behemah. If he says I suspect you of committing that you're going
to sleep with this animal, that would not apply. Okay. That's not
זנות. znus. אמר ליה רב מפשיקא לרב אשי amar lei Rav Mi'Pashika
l'Rav Ashi מנא הא מילתא דאמרי רבנן m'na ha milta d'amri rabanan
אין זנות בבהמה? ein znus b'vehemah?
Where does this come from that there's no concept of זנות znus
by a בהמה? behemah? It's a forbidden act but there's not a
concept of זנות. znus. דכתיב d'chsiv לא תביא אתנן זונה ומחיר כלב.
lo savi esnan zona u'mechir kelev. Do not bring to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash sheep that was given a gift to a prostitute
or a sheep that was exchanged for a dog. ותניא v'tanya אתנן
כלב ומחיר זונה מותרין. esnan kelev u'mechir zona mutarin. If
however it is a sheep that is given for sleeping with a
dog or a payment something that was given to buy a prostitute,
Rashi sort of says like buy a female slave, in that case
that is permissible to bring as a קרבן korban שנאמר גם שניהם,
gam sheneihem, שנים ולא ארבעה. shenayim v'lo arba'ah. Only two not four.
So because it's doesn't have the concept of payment for a זנות,
znus, payment to sleep with a dog is not considered אתנן, esnan,
that teaches you this idea that it's not conceptually זנות. znus. Okay.
So ואלא שכבת זרע למה לי? ve'ela shichvas zera lama li? Okay.
So then the גמרא Gemara says like that, okay fine. So what
is שכבת זרע shichvas zera coming to exclude? I'm sorry hold on.
Okay. So because we're not excluding a you know if the guy
can if the husband can have semen or if the person being
suspected of can have semen so what is it excluding? ואלא שכבת
זרע למה לי? ve'ela shichvas zera lama li? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibaye
lei l'chadetanya, like we to in a ברייתא. שכבת זרע פרט לדבר
אחר, shichvas zera perat l'davar acher, to exclude something
else. מאי דבר אחר? mai davar acher? אמר רב ששת פרט שקינא
לה שלא כדרכה, amar Rav Sheshes perat she'kina lah she'lo k'darkah, if
he said don't be with that man and have intercourse anal intercourse.
Okay, because that's not a type of a sleeping forgetting whether actually
semen is involved, it's not a type of sleeping that the act
of intercourse itself is not one that's in the context that you
know of becoming of conceiving. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה
רבא שלא כדרכה משכבי אשה כתיב. amar lei Rava she'lo k'darkah mishkevei
isha ksiv. But we know that that type of intercourse halachically is
considered as much intercourse as vaginal intercourse. Now you could have said
you know for all the forbidden sexual acts. Now of course you
could have said that's exactly the point here. Here it's not because
here it's all about the concern of זרע. But they don't want
to go that far once we said that she... Doesn't have to
be able to get pregnant. He doesn't need to. Nobody has to
be able to have kids. Why would we be excluding this type
of an intercourse which normally is considered to be standard intercourse? So
אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava פרט לשקינא לה דרך איברים. p'rat
leshikina lah derech evarim. If he says, "Don't have intercourse with, don't
have sex with him, you know, not anal and not and not
vaginal, but other types of sexual behavior, like oral, you know, oral
sex or other types of sexual acts." Those are not included, even
though obviously it's completely a violation of their marriage and so on,
that would not make her forbidden to her husband and that would
not be in the פרשה parsha of סוטה. So אמר ליה אביי
Amar lei Abaye פריצותא בעלמא היא. peritzuta be'alma hi.
This is mere, and it's the word "mere" is funny here, this
is mere licentiousness. Clearly it isn't an act of intercourse. Clearly it
doesn't make her forbidden. Why do I need a פסוק pasuk to
exclude it? I mean, clearly it's forbidden, but it doesn't make her
forbidden to her husband. ופריצותא מי אסר רחמנא? Uperitzuta mi assar Rachmana?
This would not make her forbidden to her husband. אלא אמר אביי
Ella amar Abaye פרט לשקינא לה בנשיקה. p'rat leshikina lah beneshikah. It's
if he said, "Don't have intercourse, don't be with that man, and
you know, and don't have intercourse even if it's just the touching
of, you know, the genitals." Okay, now it's funny because you don't
have to describe the sex act in the קינוי, but anyway, but
maybe that is not yet in the category of זרע. All right,
so the גמרא Gemara says, הניחא למאן דאמר העראה זו הכנסת עטרה.
Hani'cha leman de'amar ha'ara'ah zo hachnasat atarah. If you say that the
touching of the genitals is not yet considered the act of intercourse,
it makes sense that it's being excluded. אבל נשיקה ולא כלום הוא,
Aval neshikah velo klum hu, but נשיקה neshikah is not an act
of intercourse, היינו דאצטריך קרא למיעוטי נשיקה? Hainu de'itztarich kra lemi'utei neshikah?
It's saying that even though it's obviously highly, a hair away from
intercourse, since it's not technically intercourse, it does not make her forbidden.
אלא למאן דאמר דאמר דאמר העראה זו נשיקה, Ella leman de'amar de'amar
de'amar ha'ara'ah zo neshikah,
but according to the position that actually the touching of the genitals
on the outside is considered an act of intercourse, מאי איכא למימר,
mai ika lemimar, what can you say? Why would the תורה Torah
be excluding it? Of course תוספות Tosafot says that's exactly the point,
it's an act of intercourse, but it's not in the category of
זרע. But the גמרא doesn't want to go there. So the גמרא
says, okay, back to what you said before, לעולם לשקינא לה דרך
איברים, Le'olam leshikina lah derech evarim, fine. It's telling you that he
says don't
have sexual activity but it's not about intercourse. ומהו דתימא בקפידא דבעל
תליא מילתא? Umahu deteima bikfida deba'al talya milta? But I still might
have thought that even though it doesn't make her forbidden to her
husband, it's enough for the סוטה הלכה halacha because it's all about
the husband's, the husband being angry and upset and jealous and not
wanting it to happen, ובעל הא קא קפיד, uba'al ha ka kapid,
and he's making a point of this, קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan that that is not true, that without there being intercourse or
a concern of intercourse, we would not have the פרשה parsha of
סוטה.